so i picked them up the airport four
o'clock in the morning we went straight
to the office
and i said here's the deal
we think we found abu zubaydah he's like
you've got to be kidding me
i said i know right i mean we we've
narrowed it down but he knows we're on
his trail and so we're like 24 hours
behind him we'll bust into a safe house
and all of his stuff is there but he's
gone we went into one safe house and he
had poured himself a cup of tea and it
was still hot
but we couldn't quite
get him
so i said you got to help us narrow it
down i i just don't know what else to do
so he took this piece of butcher block
paper about the size of this table
about the size of a small american
billboard right
and he wrote
abu zubair in the center and he circled
it and then around
the name of his beta he wrote all of the
all of the
locational information that we had
for people in touch with abuza beta so
around the name of zubaida were phone
numbers addresses and email addresses
and then around that
he made a tertiary level of all the
information
of people in touch with the people who
were in touch with abu zubeda
at the end of the week it looked like a
spider web it was actually very pretty
like a like an artwork
and he came to me and he said
i just cannot get it to any fewer than
14 sites i said 14 sites
we've never hit more than two in a night
before
we can't hit 14 sites simultaneously
i said i got to get a big team in here
so i cabled headquarters
and i said
i need 36 people
i need a plane load of guns
and ammunition
i need two million dollars in cash
i made this whole list of all this stuff
why two million dollars in cash because
i'm gonna start throwing lots of money
at lots of people
bribing people
i'll bribe everybody in the country that
i need to bribe
and we needed to start buying safe
houses right if we knew that he was in
lahore faisal abad karachi islamabad
we can't be seen like leaving the
embassy driving to pakistani
intelligence we we need to
be discreet we all grew these long bushy
beards in the embassy they called me the
archbishop because mine came in all gray
right it was really long
and um
we dressed as pakistanis pakistani the
big balloon pants and the flat pancake
hats
so um
just two days later this
completely unmarked 737 lands at the
airport and
36 guys get off half cia half fbi and
then pallets and pallets of equipment it
took us hours to unload this plane
and um
and i went to introduce myself to the
[__] pakistani intelligence officer in
charge in faisalabad and he said what do
you need
for me to help you with and i said i
need a real estate agent
so
he got us a real estate agent
we bought two houses
we bought a
10 bedroom 10 bath house
in lahore
figuring we could use
the bedrooms to interrogate prisoners
and then we bought a seven bedroom seven
bath house in faisal abad it was a
doctor's house i remember
and um
and then
we
started briefing the team you know
here's what we're gonna do here's what
the plan is we got 14 sites we're gonna
have to hit every one of them
simultaneously
and i said it's never been done before
and the risk is high
right i mean it's like really high like
not all of us may make it back
so
um
on the night of the raid
my colleague who i was closest to
he and i
i'm skipping a lot of this story because
it's so long he and i were walking
back to the safe house and he said
what do you think you think we're going
to get him
and i said no
i think we're going to get somebody
but i don't think we're going to get him
he's too smart
he's outsmarted us
at every step of the way so far
so that day
we decided to drive
it was my colleague and me
the pakistani colonel and the targeting
analyst
the targeting analyst dropped off and
went back to the safe house
but we started going to every one of the
14 sites just to make sure we weren't
being set up
uh there was ingress in egress we
weren't going to be ambushed like what
happens if everything turns to [__] are
they going to be able to shoot at us
from the roofs how high are these
buildings
so
the first one we went to we realized was
a mistake it was a it was a shish kebab
stand with a pay phone
and clearly there was al qaeda living in
the neighborhood whenever they needed to
make a call they'd go to the pay phone
but the shish kabob stand closed at
midnight there's nobody there you can't
raid this shish kebab stand you got to
get anything so we cut it off the list
so we have 13 left
and
most of these places were just you know
one room mud huts
concrete block
little poor people's houses with
corrugated tin roofs
um and then we came upon
this huge house it was bright yellow
and just as we're coming up to it the
targeting analyst calls me and he says
i just got a call from
a friendly western
intelligence service
and they said that they had a a walk-in
this morning a walk-in is somebody who
literally walks in off the street and
says i have intelligence information but
i want you to pay me for it
99 of the time they're lunatics
or potential terrorists or probes like
from the iranians or the russians or the
north koreans just to see where are the
cameras
are the windows bulletproof how thick
are the doors
who's armed
we all do this to each other wow yeah
just in case they want to attack our
embassy
spooky yeah it happens all the time it's
very dangerous so
he said that this friendly intelligence
service said
that
there is a large
congregation of al-qaeda fighters and
they're in a big yellow house
and i said holy [__] i said i'm right in
front of the yellow house it's it's site
number 12.
and he said uh well then that that has
to be it i said i want to talk to the
source i want to talk to the walk-in
and he said i already asked and they
said no which made me think that there
wasn't a walk-in that it was an
intercept
but they didn't want us to know that
they were intercepting al-qaeda's
communications why wouldn't they want
you to know because we would try to take
it
okay take over their tap and you know
there's
there are a lot of pissing matches
in intelligence not just between the cia
and the fbi but then between the cia and
all of its allies and friends
it's so funny it's awful the politics
involved is ridiculous
so then
i said i said to the pakistani colonel i
said we're gonna have to
put a
big team on this one
and um he said i can tell you
that something bad is going on in that
house i said how do you figure
he said
it has to be 110 degrees right now
and all of their shutters are closed he
said it has to be broiling in there they
have something to hide
so i said okay we'll put a bigger team
on that one
so that night
at 10 o'clock
i stood on the coffee table in the safe
house
and it was
all 36 of our guys plus the original 10
that you know those of us who were there
already plus all the pakistanis right so
we've got i don't know 60 guys
and i said at the risk of sounding
melodramatic
we're gonna have to synchronize our
watches like in the movies
so we synchronized our watches
ten o'clock i still remember and i said
look here's what we're gonna do um we
actually chartered a bus
to put everybody on this bus and take
them to faisal abad because that's where
most of the targets were three of the
targets were in
in lahore and the other ten targets were
in faisalabad
and faisalabad is just one of the most
horrible places on earth
and believe me i've been i've been to 68
countries with the cia
there aren't many worse places on earth
than pakistan
wow yeah it's bad and i've been to yemen
and somalia and i've been to some of the
most horrible places on the planet and
pakistan's worse
so anyway um
i said here's the plan
oh 130 we leave the safe house
oh 145 be in the target neighborhood oh
150 be parked in your spot
0155 make sure that not only do you have
line of sight of the target but make
sure that you're not being surveilled
oh 158 get out of the car and exactly at
o200
break down the door
separate all the women and children from
the men and make sure all of the men are
cuffed
and i said
because this is an open criminal
investigation
our friends from the fbi are going to
begin collecting
evidence
which was total horseshit let me tell
you the difference between the ci and
the fbi is the fbi goes in
and they put little sticky notes on the
four walls wall one wall two wall three
wall four then they open all the drawers
and they take pictures of what's inside
the drawers
then they look for papers and they
collect all the papers okay because
they're going to build a case
cia you go in you bust down the door you
grab all the guys and you send them to
guantanamo
oh it's [__] hilarious so
we were on the roof my colleague and i
we were on the roof of the safe house at
o200 and i said to him i looked at my
watch and i said oh 200 here we go
and just as i said it
we heard this sound in the distance
boink boink boink like metal on metal
and i said
that's not good
it's two o'clock in the morning right
nobody in the country is awake
and then we hear shots fired
and i said oh man that's really not good
so i got on the walkie talkie we knew
that that that big yellow house was the
nearest
physically nearest to us so i said
um site 12 come in what's going on over
there and the guy's like you know shots
fired shots fired well we knew that
also rule number one in intelligence
operations is the the walkie-talkies
always die
right they never ever work we used to i
actually went to nsa when i got back
they wanted you to do this lessons
learned thing because this was the first
successful major capture post 911 and i
said please i said
you guys are all geniuses here right you
build these computers these super
computers we don't even know what they
do you put satellites you can't make a
battery that doesn't die after an hour
come on
like seriously it's funny the most
obvious things the things that suck the
most yeah
so we run downstairs we jump in the car
we speed over to the yellow house and
it's chaos
one of the things i told the i told the
pakistanis just before we kicked off i
said
we have to take him alive right my
orders were very specific we have to
take him alive so don't shoot unless
you're being shot at
it was clear to everybody
so we get there chaos
one guy is
dead laying dead in the street i i i can
show you some pictures i have on my
phone
another guy looks like if he's not dead
he's going to be dead in five minutes
another guy is screaming bloody murder
and has he's completely soaked in blood
and these are their guys or your guys
their guys okay
i said what the [__] happened
and this pakistani um policeman um
says to me we got him we got your man i
said
why'd you shoot them
he said that they were jumping from the
roof of the house to the roof of the
other house to escape and so he shot
them
so the first one to jump
first of all the boink point boink we
heard was the door was reinforced with
steel
and it should have just splintered with
the first hit this
they were working on you know the whole
time
abu zubaydah
a syrian bomb maker
and his and absorbed his bodyguard were
on the second floor
on the first floor there were
i'm not still not allowed to say the
number there were several dozen
fighters
al-qaeda fighters on the first floor why
wouldn't you be allowed to say the
number they still will not allow me to
say the number of people captured wow
yeah it was many dozens
so
the guys on the first floor didn't know
who was on the second floor they knew it
was a vip
because there was a
kid
they called him a tiwala this kid would
he was working for them and every day he
would go to the market and buy food and
he would cook for them and he would make
tea
and they were cut off from everybody in
the first floors they knew that somebody
important was upstairs and they wondered
if it was bin laden
yeah
so when we started breaking down the
door
abu zubaydah and the other two went to
the roof tried to jump to the roof of
the next door house and this idiot
pakistani policeman just starts picking
him off with an ak-47 the first the
first guy that jumped was the syrian
bomber
and this was a bad guy when we got onto
the second floor of that house he had
all of his bomb making stuff on the
table explosives and everything the
soldering iron was still hot because he
was making the bomb and he had the plans
to the british school
on the table he was going to blow up the
school this is how bad these people were
so um
he jumped the pakistani guy shot him
killed him instantly he was dead before
he hit the ground
the second one to jump was abu zubaydah
and the guy shot him in the thigh the
groin and the stomach
and he was bleeding out
the third guy
the pakistani policeman told me he shot
him through the leg right through the
center of his femur
so
i said
so which one's my guy
this one the middle one who was bleeding
out
i said that that doesn't look anything
like abu zubair
we had a six-year-old passport photo of
abu's beta he was a young thin good
looking
you know
short bearded mustache
closely trimmed how old
he was 24
maybe okay in this picture okay 22 okay
i said this guy he doesn't look anything
like the picture this guy was fat
clean shaven
crazy albert einstein hair going all
every direction
so i called the targeting analyst and i
said listen it's chaos here the
pakistanis shot a bunch of guys
they say we got him but this guy doesn't
look anything like abu zabeda and i
don't know what to do
and he said uh do a retinal scan right
take a picture of his of his eye
email it to me and i'll uh i'll run a
retinal scan so i i knelt down over him
and i shouted if hey nick open your eyes
if the high eunuch but his eyes
were rolled back in his head i could
just see the whites of his eyes i
couldn't see anything he was dying
and i said his eyes are rolled back in
his head i can't see anything
and he said give me a picture of his ear
i didn't know until that night that no
two people on earth have the same ears
they're like fingerprints huh yeah
so i took a picture of his ear
of course these are the days when phones
didn't have cameras
so i took a picture i plugged the camera
into the phone i sent the picture to the
analyst he sends it to cia headquarters
then they respond it's him
so
i said to my colleague i said listen
he's going to die we got to get him to a
hospital so we threw him into the back
of this
filthy
toyota pickup truck
little tiny pickup truck called a toyota
cherry
there he is the the picture right there
on the on the right in the center
that one that one yeah that's the
passport photo that we had okay
and he was six years older than that
when you captured him yes and 50 pounds
heavier why's he get the eye patch in
that photo
yeah
the eye patch is that toy is that a
result of torture
advanced interrogation enhanced
interrogation when he was fighting the
soviets uh
he got a shrapnel wound in his eye and
he was blinded in one eye okay and then
as part of his torture
uh we drugged him one day and we took
his eyeball out
which is a human rights violation it's a
crime against humanity we didn't even
ask him we didn't even tell him
they just gassed him and then when he
woke up he had no eyeball so they gave
him up oh what he was under yeah holy
[__] so
they gave him a prosthetic eyeball that
he has steadfastly refused to wear
because he said that we stole his eye
and so he insists on wearing the patch
the patch looks pretty cool though it
does actually look pretty cool
so you were standing over this guy right
here yeah in the middle of the street at
2am while he was dying bleeding out yeah
we rushed him to faisal about hospital
the worst place i've ever been in my
life
this hospital
the windows are open the doors are open
there are like dogs and cats just
walking up and down the halls there are
clouds of mosquitoes
feasting on people's open wounds
it was disgusting
and then they had this bar of irish
spring soap with needles coming out of
it and if you needed a shot they'd take
one of the syringes they'd give you your
shot and then stick it back in the bar
soap
so here we are
there are like
six americans dressed as pakistanis with
an arab who's bleeding to death
we take him into the emergency
room and i said to the doctor
i said
you've got to patch him up my orders
were to take him alive
and the guy's like looking at me like
what what's going on
we were like come on let's go
so they rush him into surgery
and the rest of us just sat down to wait
how long did the surgery take well that
was kind of a problem
word got around the al-qaeda community
that we had gotten him
and so they started driving by the
hospital and just opening fire on the
hospital and we're diving down on the
ground
while he's in the middle of surgery
because they knew we were in there with
him
[__] i said to the colonel
if they realize how lightly armed we are
we're dead
can you get a helicopter in here
and he said i i think so
so he makes a couple of calls 20 minutes
later this helicopter lands in the
parking lot
i put my shirt up over my mouth like
this i walked into the operating room
and i said doc wrap it up we got to go
so they sew them closed
we wheel them out onto the onto the
parking lot and put them on the
helicopter and we flew
to a pakistani military base about 50
miles away
now the base was kind of funny
it had a it had a small
it not really a hospital so much it was
like a clinic like a surgical clinic it
had eight beds it was in a circle and
the nurse's station was the the hub
of the wheel and then eight beds were
the spokes right and i noticed
there was a chart that had
the each patient's name and why he was
in there and every one of the patients
was in there for an attempted suicide
which was nuts to me but they had this
bed open
two beds open
and um
and so we took him in they took him
straight into surgery
so at one point the doctor came out and
he said to me
it was funny because he didn't know who
the prisoner was he didn't know who i
was but this intelligence colonel said
these are vips you got to do what they
say
so he comes out and he's like look i
don't know what this is about but i'm
going to tell you i have never seen
wounds so severe where the patient lived
so you may want to tell your people that
this is probably not going to be a good
outcome
so i called
i called the targeting analyst and he
called headquarters and they were like
do what you can
so
while he was in surgery an ambulance
arrived with the bodyguard who had been
shot through the leg
and he's screaming he's crying and
so
you know i've already been up 24 hours
at this point and my orders and these
were directly from george tenet the cia
director 24 7 cia eyes on he said those
were his exact words 24 7 cia's eyes on
don't let the [__] fbi
sit there and take over he's our
prisoner not the fbi's prisoner while
he's in surgery i i'm so sleepy already
i i'm i decide to walk around
this little clinic and i get i hear the
guy screaming and crying in the other
room so i went over to him
and i said uh kev
how are you
and he goes he's crying goes
glory to god
and i said yeah
you don't look so good
and he says are you american and i said
yeah we captured you
and he says
the pakistanis
the dogs
they captured me and then they held me
down and then they put an ak-47 on my
leg and they shot me
and i said
that's not what i heard i heard you were
jumping from the roof of the house to
the roof of the next door house to
escape
and he stops crying and he says to me
look at me
i am 150 kilos i cannot jump from the
roof
it's like 330 pounds yeah
and i pull the sheet back i'm gonna find
the pictures and show you i pull the
sheet back
and he is
not just soaked in blood
but there is a perfect
burn mark
like the size of a dinner plate
around his leg they held that ak
right on his skin
and pulled the trigger
so the doctor told me we're gonna have
to amputate the leg and i said well
that's unfortunate they ended up saving
the leg but the guy's never gonna walk
normally again oh my yeah it was pretty
it was pretty awful
and it was the pakistani soldiers that
did that yeah because the guy pissed him
off
you know he wouldn't give up so they
shot him god it was bad it was bad so
they didn't end up they did not amputate
his leg they did not amputate his leg
but i'm sure it completely shattered his
femur oh my god the damage it was
disgusting i'm looking for these
pictures while i'm talking to you and
i'm i'm amazing he didn't bleed out it
was incredible well i mean well abu is a
beta as well
and speaking of abuse
not bleeding out um
when
when he came out of surgery
um
okay here
it's not a very good picture but that's
the that's the bomb maker
he's
okay he's clearly dead yeah dead in that
picture he's on a morgue table right in
that picture
and
that's the bodyguard
oh my god as you can tell there was some
significant bleeding
yeah
and then
that is brutal it was bad
really bad
i'm going to find out was a better for
you and here's absolutely after we threw
him in the back of the pickup truck as
you can see he looks nothing like that
picture no
wow
he looks totally different totally
completely different
and i'll tell you what i said was that
by design was he doing yeah
it was a disguise right uh-huh
i saw my whole career just like go up in
smoke i was like who the heck is that
right
so anyway they finally bring him out of
surgery
and
i was really really tired
and so i was afraid i was gonna fall
asleep and i'm thinking
is the doctor secretly al-qaeda maybe
the doctor's gonna break him out or
maybe he's not as badly wounded as i
think he is and i'm gonna fall asleep
and then he's gonna get up and run away
so i tore i tore a sheet into strips and
i tied him to the bed
by the wrists and the ankles
he was bleeding
so profusely this was after surgery
after surgery okay
he was bleeding so profusely that it was
actually
pooling under the bed
i've said before it was like a scene
from a horror movie i've never seen
anything like it in my life
he was soaked in blood we had blood all
over us it's in this giant puddle
underneath the the bed so they had this
pump i had never seen anything like this
before you know how they have like blood
just dripping into your arm well they
attached a pump to it so it's forcing
the blood into your arm like at this
greatly accelerated rate because he was
bleeding so badly that they had to
replace the blood as quickly as possible
to keep him alive yeah just to keep him
alive and he was in a coma and the
doctor's like i i don't think he's gonna
make it
so i sat there with my arms crossed at
the foot of his bed
and i just stared at him
i just stared at him
and i i put the ceiling fans on full
blast to make it like slightly
uncomfortable
so that i wouldn't fall
asleep and then during the night i
called
a buddy of mine at the safe house and i
said
i said man would you do me a favor i
said i'm freaking starving first of all
i said there's about to eat abu sabha i
know right i'm starving
and i said i'm really dirty i smell
really bad i've got a clean shirt
and a pair of underwear can you bring
him
to to the hospital from the safe house
so a couple hours later he comes he's
got like these you know those little
cheese crackers and peanut butter
crackers in that pack he had a couple of
those he had a thing of orange juice and
there was a red t-shirt that my kids had
bought me for christmas with spongebob
squarepants on it
like the decal you know
and uh and he gave me my clean underwear
so i got changed
and then the next day
he started to stir
just a little bit
and so
i stood up at the foot of his bed and i
was looking down on him
and i say in my i did it again sorry
sorry i think you're good
i say in my first book you could tell
the exact instant
that he realized oh my god the americans
have me
because
he's hooked up to all these machines and
his heart rate is 110 right
and when he opens his eyes
he doesn't look at my face he looks at
spongebob
and his heart rate went to 220.
and the machine starts going b b b b b b
and then you hear code blue code blue
bay one code blue and then they rush in
and they shock him you know clear i had
never seen this before except on tv
right clear they shock him and then they
give him this shot of demerol that they
that they put right into the drip
and then he was out again
that poor bastard woke up and saw
spongebob for the first time after being
blown away by an ak-47 yeah
yeah
it was too much for him
so he was out for another six or eight
hours he saw spongebob and he knew he
was [__] he knew he was [__] it was
over
finally he opens his eyes and again
i've got him tied to the bed by the
wrists and the ankles so he's laying
there like this
and
he opens his eyes
and he goes like this like motioning for
me to come near him
so i go right next to him like i put my
ear right next to his mouth and i moved
his oxygen mask off to the side and i
said
what is your name
and he shook his head so i said again
and he said to me in english
i will not speak to you in god's
language
and i said that's okay abu zubaydah we
know who you are
and he starts crying and he says please
brother kill me take the pillow and kill
me
and i said nobody's going to kill you
we've been looking for you for a long
time
he said what's going to happen to me
and i said honestly i don't know
but i'm gonna give you some advice
i'm the nicest guy
that you're gonna meet in this
experience
my colleagues
they're not nice like i am
so if there's one thing that you do
it's that you have to cooperate
and he said you seem like a nice man but
you're the enemy and i'll never
cooperate
i said suit yourself
so i sit back down
he wants to talk what happened i said
well you're jumping from the roof he
remembered going to the roof
i said you tried to jump and pakistani
guys shot you
and
i said you're
severely wounded it's going to take a
long time for you to to recover
but listen
you should take this time to do the
right thing
a lot of people are going to ask you a
lot of questions and you have to be
honest
and he said no
that he didn't know anything about 911
that all he ever wanted to do was kill
jews he said that he didn't want to
attack the united states he wanted to
attack israel
and they outvoted him
we talked you know one of the things
that we that we captured that night was
his diary
and
books have been written two books have
been written about his diary
one of the fbi psychologists said it was
the rantings of a madman
it's like well clearly you and i didn't
read the same diary right because really
what it was it was more of a doodle book
than anything else he would doodle draw
pictures
and he would write poems
he recited a lot of his poetry to me you
read it oh yeah all of it oh yeah yeah
okay uh-huh
and then i consulted on one of the books
so um
one of the things that he did and this
is weird he's a strange guy
you know he's not a guy that you're
going to want to go out and have a beer
with sorry interrupt how old was he at
this time
30 29 or 30 30.
he had this weird thing that he would do
where he would write letters to himself
as a young man or as a teenager
so it's the 30 year old abzu beta
writing to the 14 year old that was a
beta and giving himself advice to his
past self to his past self
listen you should have done it this way
oh you shouldn't have gone out with uh
those guys they were bad guys you know
you should have been kinder to your
mother on this day
stuff like that it was weird
but it was
expressive he's he's a very artistic
kind of person
so you draw these pictures and he would
write poems and he would write a scene
from a play
and then he would write a letter to
himself and the fbi is like clearly he's
insane it's like no he's not freaking
insane
it's a doodle book
so anyway
oh my god how we we fought about that
for years
really yeah
yeah
because they said he was insane anyway
um
well he was just a kid yeah he was a kid
right where
i don't know how old you are but now i
mean in my mind i'm still 20 but but i'm
actually 57 and i have to remind myself
you're not 20 anymore right i wish i was
and i think back on things that i would
have done differently i've never
actually written it down anywhere but
right you know sometimes people do
so um
so what happened to him after that after
that
visit with him in the hospital when you
were talking to him and well i never
left
i never left and then finally one of my
colleagues came and said uh listen
uh we gotta get him ready to go uh
they're sending a plane in
and i said where's he gonna go
and my friend is like i don't have any
idea
so
at
i told him i said listen uh we're gonna
take you out of this place and you're
going somewhere else
and he said are they gonna kill me and i
said no
i said i don't know what's gonna happen
to you but
i can guarantee that you are going to
get the best medical care that the
american government can provide
and i'm going to tell you again you have
to cooperate
and i said i don't mean to sound they
really wanted to keep him alive oh yeah
they did they had big plans for him i
said
i don't mean to sound cruel
but your life is over
it's over
you'll never be free again
and so the rest of it
can be easy
or it can be terrible
and it's up to you
so
i told him a plane is coming and it's
going to take you to someplace else i
don't know where that is
so he
asked me if i would hold his hand
so three fbi agents and i picked him up
you know his gurney
i'm holding his hand with one hand and
holding onto the gurney with the other
we take him out to the plane
and we had to lift him up like to a
standing position to maneuver him onto
the plane and then we laid him across
the luggage rack at the back
and we tied the gurney down to the
luggage rack
and i said i leaned over and i said
remember you have to cooperate and he
squeezed my hand and i said good luck
and then as i'm getting off the plane
one of these cia dudes who was wearing
completely black with a black hood he
says to me john
and i go yeah who are you and he lifts
up his
his hood why was he wearing a hood
everybody was wearing hoods
yeah it's weird
they didn't want to be recognized this
was the rendition team so this is like
the most secret of all the secret things
that the cia does
right these international kidnappings so
they didn't want him to see their faces
and
i said who are you and he lifts up his
mask just a little bit and he was my
last boss at the cia he goes what are
you doing here no [__] yeah and i said
oh i said man we've been doing raids we
we got this as our first hvt high value
target
and he said who is he
and i said dude i'm sorry you don't have
a need to know
i'm not allowed to say who he is
and he said no no that's cool i said
where are you taking him
and he goes oh dude you don't have a
need to know i'm so sorry i said no no i
said godspeed wherever you're going i
hope you have safe travels
and um and then he took off and i never
saw him again
but he was going to guantanamo no no no
no no it was years before he got to
guantanamo really so he went to one of
those black sites he went to six of
those
six of the black sites now what's the
deal with the black sites the cia black
sites what for people who don't know
what they are they sound so [__]
mysterious yeah they are
this is this is bad
this is how how secret this is
a black site is a secret facility
usually housed on a foreign military
base
right i'm not allowed to say any of the
countries even though they've all been
reported on in the media the cia has
never admitted to the to the existence
of black sites
and so i
i i can't confirm
their locations but i can say
google it and the locations yeah so um
many of these black sites the presidents
and prime ministers of the countries
that they were in had no idea that they
were there really these were
secret
unwritten handshake agreements between
the directors the director of the cia
and the director of that country's
intelligence service
so in many cases even the ministers of
defense
didn't know that these secret cia
torture facilities were on their
military bases in their countries
that's how secret they were
and then if
you know somebody would say oh what
what's that building over there you know
we haven't used that building in years
and i've been seeing people coming in
and out of it lately two days later
buildings abandoned
everybody's in a different country
that's what they would do so you go from
country a to country b to c d e f
although the cia has been doing this
stuff for decades right i mean all the
way back yeah all the way back to like
those lsd experiments they were doing
they were doing tests on people in
different countries that's right because
they didn't want to violate the laws
that's right
yeah i went back to the safe house i i
slept for a while after abzu beta took
off i went back to the safe house and um
there was one incident that
that happened
that i was 1 000 right about that dogged
me later when i got back to headquarters
we had done that night one of the raids
that we did was
was a mistake
it was a girl's school
in
a private house
and what happened was this
house
was an old man in his 70s and his two
sons and their wives
they had the only phone in the
neighborhood and so people would come
over and say hey can i use the phone and
the old man would say sure give me five
rupees they'd give him five rupees
they'd make a call well they're calling
you know osama bin laden
so
we were like oh my god that that phone
that house it's like a headquarters of
al-qaeda
we bust down the door
we grabbed this old man and his sons
and they were scared shitless right
so
there was this idiot working for me
he brings them to the safe house he's
got his three prisoners cuffed behind
their backs and they have these black
hoods on
and i said
why are they hooded
he goes why are they hooded we don't
want them to see our faces and i said
are you seriously [__] telling me
that you have never read the geneva
convention it is a war crime to hood
your prisoners
take the hoods off
and he goes dude if you take those hoods
off i'm reporting you to headquarters i
said i'm reporting you to headquarters
for committing a war crime now take the
hoods off
so i pulled the hoods off
turns out these three guys were
completely
innocent of anything they just happened
to have the only phone in the
neighborhood
so i said to the pakistanis
what can i do to make it right for these
people because this is going to be a pr
disaster this is like the most secret
thing we've done in 20 years
and these guys are you know they're
going to tell everybody
the americans broke down the door my
house they took me they put hoods on me
and my kids and
you know it was awful and he
said he said give him a hundred dollars
each
so
i said to the old man i said sir
we've made a terrible mistake and on
behalf of the president of the united
states i apologize to you and to your
family and i hope that you will take
this money to repair the damage that
we've done to your home
and he said
that he accepted my apology
the very next day
there he is on the news
the pakistani news standing in front of
the destroyed door
and he said it was the americans they
broke down the door of my house they
took my sons and me we don't know where
we were but they were very polite and
they bought us new shoes
so it kind of went away it was a one-day
story
wow yeah oh so i get back to
headquarters and they ream me out
because i took the hoods off
and i said it's a war crime why does
nobody understand this you know there
are rules for these kinds of things that
we're doing
if we're really the good guys then let's
be the good guys and these are all
pakistani guys you're talking to no
they're americans they're all our people
okay yeah and you didn't think it was
weird that you were the only guy that
was like really worried about i just
figured they were all retards okay
you were the only one that was worried
about the hood like no one else hadn't
even batted an eye at it yeah no they're
like yeah who cares huh there are
prisoners they're terrorists we're the
good guys
don't you think it's weird i always
thought it was super strange how um like
just after you tell that story about
about um
abu what's his name abu zubeda um
that bin laden when they captured bin
laden they killed him instantly right
yeah they never had any intention of
taking him alive is it is it weird to
you that they never like brought his
body back to the u.s no no i i i would
have expected that they would destroy
the body i i was hoping a lot of my
colleagues and i hoped that they would
bring him back alive because i mean talk
about the triumph of of law and order
right talk about the triumph of a
constitutional democracy
ah we just blew him away which is fine
too i mean the guy committed horrible
crimes and killed thousands of americans
but i i was hoping that we could set an
example for the rest of the world
by putting him on trial finding him
guilty and executing him
i thought i just thought i mean i could
be wrong but i thought it was like
standard practice to even if we do get
get and kill we kill those high value
targets that we bring their bodies back
to give them to autopsy and do like dna
normally yes
well the dna we took dna
see his his family
the bin laden family is one of the most
important merchant families in saudi
arabia right they're worth many billions
of dollars and they're the they have the
biggest construction company in in the
kingdom they do the big stuff like
airports and and ports and you know
is it currently like that too they're
still still the biggest fans oh yeah oh
wow yeah
um i know his was his sister or his
daughter or something lives in
uh israel or something there's one that
lives here in uh in orlando
really
there's one that lives in beverly hills
there's one that lives in are these
children of his uh-huh okay not not of
osama
of the old man
oh of his dad okay yeah
yeah he had like
65 sons and 40-something daughters jesus
yeah right a whole bunch of wives
um and you know this osama's the one
that went he went bad
so
you know
as soon as it was clear
that it was
that it was al qaeda that did 9 11
his family just
volunteered like we want to give you dna
so when you kill him you can be sure
that it's him we said great because you
know when you get hit with one of these
drone rockets
there's going to be a shoulder over
there and a foot over there and
some scalp over there
it's not like you can look at the body
and say oh that's osama bin laden he's
in pieces normally right
so we had the dna but what they the
reason why they threw the body overboard
is that what they did they threw it off
a ship yeah yeah they flew it out to a
ship why the [__] would they do that
because they didn't want it to become a
source of reverence
they didn't want it to be you know
a mecca for terrorists or inspirational
for terrorists so they figured if they
destroyed it there'd be no place for
anybody to go to
to revere it
how would it inspire terrorists if we
did an autopsy on them well it's the
same reason that that you know hitler
was
the soviets cremated hitler and threw
his ashes in a river
you just don't want people you don't
want a rallying point for people
and we didn't didn't really need the
autopsy because we had the dna
okay you could just sort of do a
pseudo-autopsy later right
yeah they they had a muslim cleric on
board
a naval
chaplain who's a muslim
and uh he did all the funeral prayers
they wrapped him up in a shroud and they
threw him over the side
wow the pictures are video of it or
anything no in fact the president was
very very specific about that really oh
yeah
but even though we showed video of uh
hussein being hung yeah well that
slipped out
one of the executioners uh did it on his
phone
okay that wasn't official that was also
pretty brutal yeah yeah hey
oh sorry to his right okay
okay
yeah weird stuff it's crazy
um
what were you just talking about
um the body going overboard oh yeah yeah
the body so okay so where where is uh
abu zubat well i
right now so in 2006
uh after four years going from secret
site to secret site right okay six years
he was going from black side to black
site yeah so we sent him to guantanamo
in 2006 and he's been there ever since
there was a very interesting article in
the new york times
two weeks ago i guess it was
carol rosenbloom
is
the only reporter
anywhere that covers these issues nobody
cares anymore about abzu beta
i mean this is ancient history it
happened 20 years ago
a little bit more than 20 years ago he
doesn't have any actionable intelligence
anymore the information's a generation
old so nobody cares except for her
and she broke this story two weeks ago
that there are negotiations underway
by abu zubaydah's attorneys khalid
sheikh muhammad's attorney policing a
little bit closer under you this one
yeah just pull it pull it right under
you it's a little bit oh sorry you
scooted and that thing didn't oh that's
right
um absolutely attorneys khalid sheikh
mohammed's attorneys ramsey beneshib
um omar baloch and maybe one other
to negotiate a guilty plea
uh
you know only khalid sheikh muhammad has
ever been charged with a crime abuse
bait has never been charged with a crime
any crime
there's a ton of guys there that haven't
been charged with crimes right well
almost none of them have yeah only
khalid sheikh muhammad so the deal is
they will agree to plead guilty to
terrorism
and conspiracy to commit terrorism
and in exchange will give them life
without parole
but will allow them to remain at
guantanamo for the rest of their lives
what they're worried about
they now realize after 20 plus years
they're not getting out
so what they want is
they don't want to go to
um
to the super max in florence colorado
the weather's terrible it's cold they
don't like the cold they want to stay in
cuba
so that's what the deal is going to end
up being wow
wow have you heard have you ever heard
the story have you ever been to
guantanamo once
what when was that
summer of 2002
after we had caught up azerbaija before
we had caught khalid sheikh muhammad but
before abzu beta arrived there
yeah wow packed was it really packed
yeah
that's so good and you know what's funny
i i have some like regular contacts now
who were prisoners there
like i'm friendly with
muhammad ultslahi
from mauritania that poor guy i mean
there were so many innocent people i
heard a story about a guy named latif
nasir there was like another guy in
canada with the same exact name he did
this like long podcast story about the
guy and had contact with him or through
his attorney yes
there are there are several stories like
that have you ever heard of maher arar
no also canadian
so mahara
was
is a political science professor at the
university of toronto
and um he's ethnically tunisian
he's a naturalized canadian citizen and
he's been a political science professor
for a long time
so he went
in
2001 he went to tunisia to visit some
cousins of his
and
a woman that i was working for at the
time said
this guy is a bad guy maher
we even had staff meetings about him
and there were several of us there were
three of us i was one of the three who
said uh uh
you guys don't speak arabic that's what
the problem is
there's a bad guy who has a name that
sounds like maher arar
but it's not maher
this guy is a freaking political science
professor
she says
grab him
so we asked the fbi to grab him at
kennedy airport when he flew back from
tunisia
the fbi grabs him they turn him over to
the cia the cia turns him over to syrian
intelligence
right syrian intelligence
they tortured this guy mercilessly for
10 months they gave him electroshock to
his balls they pulled his fingernails
out they raped him they did uh what do
you call it sleep deprivation
they made him a a whimpering
mush of a man
and then the syrians came back to us and
they said listen we think this is the
wrong guy
this guy doesn't know anything
we broke him
and so we said uh let him go
in the meantime
his wife is waiting for him
at the airport in toronto he was
supposed to get off the plane at kennedy
and get a connection to toronto he never
gets on the plane or gets off the plane
so his wife asks you know what's up
and um
and the faa said oh no he never got on
the plane in uh in tunisia
but then a month later she gets a credit
card bill and here he had bought her a
pair of sunglasses on the duty free on
the plane
and she said look i have proof he was on
the plane he bought a pair of sunglasses
from the duty free
and they were like uh yeah
we don't know what's going on sorry
so finally he was released
and he's like
they snatched me off the plane with
these fbi badges then the cia took me
then the syrians tortured me for the
last 10 months he filed a
20 million dollar lawsuit against the
u.s government
filed it in the eastern district of
virginia in alexandria
and the cia goes to the eastern district
uh court and they said uh national
security your honor we can't talk about
any of this sources and methods
and the judge is like case dismissed
so
wow
so nothing happened he sued the canadian
government because we informed the
canadians you have an al-qaeda guy
working at the university of toronto
and he wasn't
so the canadians gave him six million
dollars
but the last time i spoke to him he told
me that he has not left his house
in 14 years
he has such terrible
anxiety disorder now and agoraphobia
that he has not left the four walls of
his house in 14 years good [__] lord
that's crazy
yeah if you if you don't mind
i'll tell you about another one there's
a guy named khalid al-masri
the name al-masri means the egyptian
it's not even really a name it's just
this guy goes by khalid his name is
khalid
he
owned a
he owned a little grocery store in
berlin
and
he got in a fight with his wife one
night
and their marriage was lousy and he just
decided i'm out of here
and so he gets on a bus
to go to macedonia to visit his brother
he just needs to get away from his wife
in the meantime
there's this guy named khalid who's
egyptian
so his he would be khalid
al-masri
right
and he's on the phone saying hey
i want to blow up the american embassy
in albania
so we get a tip that there's this guy
khalid al-masri who wants to blow up the
american embassy and there's this guy
khalid al-masri who's on a bus on the
way to uh to macedonia we send in this
team with a helicopter
coming down and they stop the bus and
they snatch him off the bus
and they send him to egypt and we tell
the egyptians
soften him up a little bit
tell us what the plans are to blow up
our embassy in
albania he didn't know what the [__] we
were talking about
so he's there
for a year same thing with him they
electrocute him they beat him they rape
him they pull his fingernails out
and then they come back to us and
they're like
you know there are like 50 million
people named khaled al-masri this is not
the guy you're looking for
[Music]
you